What do you think would happen if you dropped two balls side-by-side at the same time?
You'd think they'd fall in parallel and never hit each other, right?
Actually, strictly speaking, that's not quite right.
Exploring this question leads us to the heart of general relativity: the curvature of spacetime.
Let's say you're sitting in a chair right now watching this video.
There's a tiny difference in distance from the center of the Earth between your head and your feet.
Since your feet are closer to Earth, they feel a slightly stronger gravity.
As a result, your body is actually being stretched vertically.
Unless you're watching this while doing a handstand!
Of course, this effect is so small it's invisible to the naked eye.
But this stretching, caused by spacetime curvature and tidal forces, is the core of general relativity.
Today, let's use this as a clue to intuitively understand what 'spacetime curvature' actually is.
Before we dive into curvature and tidal forces, let's consider: what exactly is gravity anyway?
What would happen if you were on a plane and the engines suddenly stopped?
Inside a plane in freefall, you would experience weightlessness, just like in this video.
Everyone looks like they're having fun!
This is actually the same principle as why astronauts float inside the Space Station.
Because the Space Station is constantly falling around the Earth, those inside feel weightless.
To someone in freefall, it feels as if gravity has completely vanished.
If you were in a windowless box, you couldn't tell if you were falling, in orbit, or in deep space where gravity is weak.
Gravity and acceleration are locally indistinguishable. We call this the equivalence principle.
Einstein reportedly called this 'the happiest thought' of his life.
But if gravity can be canceled out, doesn't it make you wonder if gravity even truly exists?
In fact, there is a 'real' gravitational effect that even freefall cannot eliminate.
That is the tidal force we mentioned earlier.
Let's look specifically at what this 'un-cancelable gravity' really looks like.
Imagine two balls side-by-side, dropped simultaneously toward the Earth.
What would happen to them?
They seem like they should fall in parallel and never touch.
But strictly speaking, they don't.
This is because the Earth is a sphere.
Gravity pulls everything toward the Earth's center.
So, both balls fall toward that same center, meaning they slowly drift together and would eventually collide.
Now, let's try dropping two balls vertically, one above the other.
Which one falls faster?
The answer is the one on the bottom.
The ball closer to Earth feels stronger gravity, so it falls faster and the gap between them widens.
The two balls gradually move further apart as they fall.
What would this look like from inside a plane that is also in freefall?
Because they're falling with the plane, the balls appear to be floating inside.
Yet, horizontal balls move together, and vertical balls move apart.
Even in 'zero-g,' the balls move as if acting on their own.
Gravity is supposed to be indistinguishable from acceleration, yet inside that falling plane, there's still movement.
This is tidal force—the real gravitational effect caused by gravity varying from one point to another.
This same tidal force is what causes the ocean tides.
The moon's gravity is stronger on the side of Earth facing it than the side away. That difference pulls on the sea.
'Spaghettification' near a black hole is just an extreme example of this tidal force.
Near a black hole, the difference in gravity between your head and feet is so massive you'd be stretched out like a noodle.
Tidal force is the 'true' gravity; measuring it tells you if you are actually in a gravitational field.
Now for the main point: this tidal force IS spacetime curvature.
Recall the two balls: horizontal ones drifted together, while vertical ones drifted apart.
To an observer in freefall, they seem to move despite there being no local gravity.
That is exactly what we mean when we say spacetime is curved.
On flat paper, parallel lines stay parallel. But in curved space, they don't.
The spherical Earth is a perfect example. We call the path of a freefalling object a 'geodesic'.
A geodesic is the shortest path in curved spacetime. A falling object follows this straightest possible path.
The change in distance between two geodesics is called 'geodesic deviation.' The balls moving is just that.
In the 19th century, Bernhard Riemann created a mathematical way to describe how these lines converge or diverge.
This is today's star: Riemann Curvature.
Riemann curvature measures how much two nearby falling objects accelerate toward or away from each other.
Einstein realized that Riemann curvature is the curvature of spacetime, which is gravity itself.
Tidal forces arise from geodesic deviation; the more spacetime curves, the stronger the tidal force.
Tidal forces, geodesic deviation, and Riemann curvature are just different ways to describe the same concept.
So, the rise and fall of the tides is actually a everyday sign of spacetime curvature.
If you enjoy fishing, you could say you're out there reacting to the curvature of spacetime.
To understand curvature even better, let's look at parallel transport.
Even simple movement across curved spacetime leads to strange results.
Imagine you're in a room, pointing south, and you walk in a circle.
If you keep pointing south and return to the start, your finger is still pointing in the original direction, right?
That seems obvious, but on a curved surface like Earth, something else happens.
Stand at the North Pole, point south, and walk down to the equator.
At the equator, walk 90 degrees east along the line while still pointing your finger in that same direction.
Then, head straight back up to the North Pole. What direction are you pointing now?
Incredibly, your finger is now 90 degrees off from where it started.
Even though you never 'turned' your hand, the direction changed. That is another definition of curved space.
You can't maintain the same orientation if the space you're moving through is curved.
We used the Earth as an example, but spacetime curves the same way around massive objects like black holes.
Gravity can appear to vanish in a falling plane, making it seem like it's gone.
But tidal force is the essential gravitational effect that cannot be erased.
Riemann curvature describes this mathematically, and Einstein used it to define spacetime curvature in general relativity.
Even the tides in the ocean are connected to the very essence of gravity. Until next time!
See you in the next video. Have a good day!